<codeBook xmlns="ddi:codebook:2_5" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="ddi:codebook:2_5 https://ddialliance.org/Specification/DDI-Codebook/2.5/XMLSchema/codebook.xsd" version="2.5"><docDscr><citation><titlStmt><titl>Qualified Personnel Monitoring 2009: Company Survey 2009</titl><IDNo agency="DOI">doi:10.11587/MUXTOK</IDNo></titlStmt><distStmt><distrbtr source="archive">AUSSDA</distrbtr><distDate>2020-06-24</distDate></distStmt><verStmt source="archive"><version date="2025-12-18" type="RELEASED">1</version></verStmt><biblCit>Hudler-Seitzberger, Michaela; Bittner, Marc, 2020, "Qualified Personnel Monitoring 2009: Company Survey 2009", https://doi.org/10.11587/MUXTOK, AUSSDA, V1</biblCit></citation></docDscr><stdyDscr><citation><titlStmt><titl>Qualified Personnel Monitoring 2009: Company Survey 2009</titl><IDNo agency="DOI">doi:10.11587/MUXTOK</IDNo><IDNo agency="WISDOM number">PLG200902</IDNo></titlStmt><rspStmt><AuthEnty affiliation="Paul Lazarsfeld Gesellschaft für Sozialforschung">Hudler-Seitzberger, Michaela</AuthEnty><AuthEnty affiliation="Paul Lazarsfeld Gesellschaft für Sozialforschung">Bittner, Marc</AuthEnty><othId role="Data Collector">market, Institut für Markt-, Meinungs- und Mediaforschung</othId></rspStmt><prodStmt><grantNo agency="Federal Ministry of Labour, Social Affairs and Consumer Protection">N/A</grantNo><grantNo agency="Ministry of Construction and Regional Development of the Slovak Republic">N/A</grantNo><grantNo agency="Cross-border Cooperation Programme Slovakia-Austria 2007-2013">N/A</grantNo></prodStmt><distStmt><distrbtr source="archive">AUSSDA</distrbtr><distrbtr>The Austrian Social Science Data Archive</distrbtr><contact affiliation="The Austrian Social Science Data Archive" email="info@aussda.at">AUSSDA</contact><depositr>Paul Lazarsfeld-Gesellschaft für Sozialforschung</depositr></distStmt><serStmt><serName>LAMO</serName><serInfo>The aim of LAMO (Labourmarket Monitoring) is the development, application and validation of a monitoring tool for the regular survey of the changes on the labour market in the course of the EU enlargement.</serInfo></serStmt><holdings URI="https://doi.org/10.11587/MUXTOK"/></citation><stdyInfo><subject><keyword xml:lang="en">Social Sciences</keyword><keyword vocab="ELSST" vocabURI="https://elsst.cessda.eu/id">Businesses</keyword><keyword vocab="ELSST" vocabURI="https://elsst.cessda.eu/id">Economic and social development</keyword><keyword vocab="ELSST" vocabURI="https://elsst.cessda.eu/id">Economic integration</keyword><keyword vocab="ELSST" vocabURI="https://elsst.cessda.eu/id">European economic community</keyword><keyword vocab="ELSST" vocabURI="https://elsst.cessda.eu/id">Human settlement</keyword><keyword vocab="ELSST" vocabURI="https://elsst.cessda.eu/id">International relations</keyword><keyword vocab="ELSST" vocabURI="https://elsst.cessda.eu/id">Workers</keyword><topcClas vocab="CESSDA Topic Classification" vocabURI="https://vocabularies.cessda.eu/vocabulary/TopicClassification">Employment</topcClas><topcClas vocab="CESSDA Topic Classification" vocabURI="https://vocabularies.cessda.eu/vocabulary/TopicClassification">Labour and employment</topcClas><topcClas vocab="CESSDA Topic Classification" vocabURI="https://vocabularies.cessda.eu/vocabulary/TopicClassification">Social and occupational mobility</topcClas></subject><abstract>In the Interreg III A project LAMO I and LAMO II, the Paul Lazarsfeld Society, together with other experts, developed a set of monitoring instruments that provided data on changes in the labour market - with particular regard to the potential of cross-border commuters and migrant workers. These data were intended to serve as a information basis and argumentation for political decision-makers and for the economy. The project "Fachkräftemonitoring" (FAMO) represents a further development and focuses in particular on the topic of skilled labour demand in Vienna and in western Slovakia (Bratislava, Trnava). The aim of FAMO, in addition to a comprehensive presentation of the economic development in the Austrian-Slovak CENTROPE region, is to obtain information on the demand for personnel (especially skilled workers) in the research region, on the basis of a large company survey and to sound out the prevailing working conditions. The FAMO company survey also interrogates realised or intended internationalization steps and cooperation between Austrian companies and companies in Western Slovakia. In addition, a survey of the employable population analysed the willingness of people to work abroad and their qualifications. Prospect Unternehmensberatung conducted qualitative interviews with company representatives in order to gain a deeper insight into the demand for skilled workers in selected industry segments. Furthermore, experts from the following areas were interviewed: regional actors from the labour market and economy as well as local decision-makers in the study regions (public federal and regional administration, labour market service, chamber of commerce, trade unions, chambers of labour, industrialists association) as well as regional managers, scientists and mayors of municipalities/cities close to the border: Sociodemographic questions, qualifications and knowledge, professional situation, wage expectations, professional and spatial mobility, experience with working abroad, experience with internal commuting, willingness and motivation to work or emigrate abroad. New questions in FAMO: Attitude towards tax evasion and undeclared work (irregular sector).</abstract><sumDscr><collDate cycle="P1" event="start" date="2008-11">2008-11</collDate><collDate cycle="P1" event="end" date="2009-02">2009-02</collDate><nation>Austria</nation><nation>Slovakia</nation><nation>Slovakia</nation><geogCover>Vienna</geogCover><geogCover>Bratislava</geogCover><geogCover>Trnava</geogCover><anlyUnit>Organization</anlyUnit><dataKind>Numeric</dataKind></sumDscr><notes>&lt;p>&lt;b>A licence to use the data and other files has not been specified and needs clarification. Unless stated otherwise the copyright statement for all files that can be downloaded is: All rights reserved. Please contact &lt;a href="mailto:info@aussda.at">info@aussda.at&lt;/a> if you would like to get access to the data.&lt;/b>&lt;/p></notes></stdyInfo><method><dataColl><timeMeth>Cross-section</timeMeth><sampProc>Non-probability: Quota</sampProc><collMode>Self-administered questionnaire: Paper</collMode><resInstru>Structured questionnaire</resInstru><sources><dataSrc>Population group</dataSrc></sources></dataColl><notes type="Additional Information on Sampling:">Quota selection according to specific economic structural conditions: Sector affiliation, company size and ownership. The structure of the sampling plan focused the survey on the tertiary sector (83% of companies). Only 1.5% of Slovak enterprises were to belong to the primary sector, the rest to manufacturing. The number of employees should exceed 200 for 20% of the companies in the secondary sector and 15% in the tertiary sector, while "only" 45% of the material goods producers and 50% of the service companies should have less than 20 employees. Medium and large enterprises are over-represented due to the sampling plan. This approach is appropriate because large enterprises are of above-average importance for the analysis of internationalisation activities and, in a random survey, the number of medium-sized and large enterprises would be too small to make reliable statements about these enterprises. Another requirement was that 20% of Slovak enterprises were (at least partially) foreign owned.</notes><anlyInfo/></method><dataAccs><setAvail/><useStmt/><notes type="DVN:TOA" level="dv">To access the files, users need to log in.</notes><notes type="DVN:TOU" level="dv">&lt;a href="https://aussda.at/en/licence-needs-clarification">Licence needs clarification&lt;/a></notes></dataAccs><othrStdyMat><relPubl><citation><titlStmt><titl>Hierländer, Peter / Nowotny, Klaus (2009): FAMO I: Das Arbeitskräfteangebot im irregulären Sektor. Ein Vergleich der CENTROPE-Regionen Wien und Bratislava-Trnava. Wien: Österreichisches Institut für Wirtschaftsforschung Hierländer, Peter / Nowotny, Klaus (2009): FAMO I: Migrations- und Pendelpotentiale in Wien und den slowakischen Grenzregionen zu Österreich. Wien: Österreichisches Institut für Wirtschaftsforschung Huber, Peter (2009): FAMO I: Wirtschaftliche Entwicklung in der CENTROPE-Region seit der EU-Erweiterung. Wien: Österreichisches Institut für Wirtschaftsforschung Pennerstorfer, Dieter (2009): Internationalisierung und Wahl der Markteintrittsform. Bestimmungsgründe und Unterschiede zwischen Unternehmen aus Wien und der Region Bratislava-Trnava. Wien: Österreichisches Institut für Wirtschaftsforschung</titl></titlStmt><biblCit>Hierländer, Peter / Nowotny, Klaus (2009): FAMO I: Das Arbeitskräfteangebot im irregulären Sektor. Ein Vergleich der CENTROPE-Regionen Wien und Bratislava-Trnava. Wien: Österreichisches Institut für Wirtschaftsforschung Hierländer, Peter / Nowotny, Klaus (2009): FAMO I: Migrations- und Pendelpotentiale in Wien und den slowakischen Grenzregionen zu Österreich. Wien: Österreichisches Institut für Wirtschaftsforschung Huber, Peter (2009): FAMO I: Wirtschaftliche Entwicklung in der CENTROPE-Region seit der EU-Erweiterung. Wien: Österreichisches Institut für Wirtschaftsforschung Pennerstorfer, Dieter (2009): Internationalisierung und Wahl der Markteintrittsform. Bestimmungsgründe und Unterschiede zwischen Unternehmen aus Wien und der Region Bratislava-Trnava. Wien: Österreichisches Institut für Wirtschaftsforschung</biblCit></citation></relPubl></othrStdyMat></stdyDscr><otherMat ID="f2056" URI="https://data.aussda.at/api/access/datafile/2056" level="datafile"><labl>10264_qu_de_v1_0.pdf</labl><txt>Questionnaire German</txt><notes level="file" type="DATAVERSE:CONTENTTYPE" subject="Content/MIME Type">application/pdf</notes></otherMat><otherMat ID="f2058" URI="https://data.aussda.at/api/access/datafile/2058" level="datafile"><labl>10264_qu_sk_v1_0.pdf</labl><txt>Questionnaire Slovak</txt><notes level="file" type="DATAVERSE:CONTENTTYPE" subject="Content/MIME Type">application/pdf</notes></otherMat><otherMat ID="f2057" URI="https://data.aussda.at/api/access/datafile/2057" level="datafile"><labl>10264_rr_de_v1_0.pdf</labl><txt>Research Report</txt><notes level="file" type="DATAVERSE:CONTENTTYPE" subject="Content/MIME Type">application/pdf</notes></otherMat></codeBook>